Where are you going to start?
Good morning. I'm going to start, we're going to start from the
top of ק"ה עמוד א' Kuf Heh Amud Aleph on the second
line where we have רבה בר רב
הונא. Rabba Bar Rav Huna. Today's the 15th of Av, ט"ו באב,
Tu B'Av, it's July 27th, and Rabbi Linzer is not here. I'm
Dan Margulies filling in for him. And we're picking up a little
bit in the middle of a conversation.
We could just backtrack a little bit.
Well, we could backtrack a little bit, but...
Yeah, because I didn't get to, you know what happened yesterday.
I don't really have a good sense of where all of this
starts. That's the problem.
105... Top of 105A is the משנה. Mishna.
Oh right, but that's mid...
No, no, no, not... at the end of 105... we're doing on
top of 105. No, I'm sorry, the one at the end of
104A is the משנה. Mishna.
Right, but that's what I mean. But I'm trying to find
where the סוגיא Sugya actually...
Okay.
From the אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא אליבא דמאן דאמר. Amar Rabbi
Yirmiah Bar Abba Aliba DeMan DeAmar. I think sort of from the
last of the skinny lines on ק"ד Kuf Daled we could start
from there. So we have this debate about... or different kinds... I
mean I wanted to start from רבה בר רב הונא Rabba Bar
Rav Huna because of that. But anyway,
so אמר רבי ירמיה בר אבא אליבא דמאן דאמר עדיין לא הגיע
זמנו לצאת מי אמרינן הני מילי בשר דאין סופו לצאת חובה אבל
הני דסופן לצאת חובה לא. Amar Rabbi Yirmiah Bar Abba Aliba DeMan
DeAmar Adayin Lo Higia Zmano Latzeit Mi Amrinan Hane Milei Bassar De’ein
Sofo Latzeit Chova Aval Hane Desofan Latzeit Chova Lo. So the question
of which kind of things will become מטמא בגדים Metamei Vegadim because
is it only those which the meat of them is going to
be taken outside and burned? Is that why... that's when you assess
it from? Because if there's going to be an obligation to take
them outside and burn them, then those are the ones that... או
דילמא הני מילי הכא נמי לא הגיע זמנו לצאת. O Dilma Hane
Milei Hachnami Lo Higia Zmano Latzeit. So if it's not yet ready
to be taken out, basically we see the rule, which we're going
to have a question about, which is that if the sacrifice has
not yet reached the stage where it would be taken out, that
is there are still further steps to do before it's taken out,
then at that point if it is taken out it will not
be מטמא בגדים Metamei Vegadim because it was sort of incomplete. It's
sort of like some of the rules of פיגול. Pigul. Like... or
maybe it's not really like that, but just trying to think of...
like you have to have done everything correctly until now in order
for then the next consequence to take effect.
Okay, so תא שמע דתני לוי שאירע בו פסול ביציאתו. Tashma DeTani
Levi She’eira Bo Psul Beyetziato. So there's a ברייתא Baraita that says
that a לוי Levi who had a פסול, Psul, which in this
case it sounds like it probably means he had a seminal emission
and became
טמא, Tamei, so ביציאתו Beyetziato when he left, or he became טמא
Tamei in some other way perhaps, or he lost a finger, I
don't know. So מאי לאו פסול יציאה? Mai Lav Psul Yetzia? So
does that reference actually the פסול יציאה Psul Yetzia of actually having
left the בית המקדש? Beit HaMikdash? We say לא פסול טומאה. Lo
Psul Tuma. It's really the פסול Psul that comes about by becoming
טמא Tamei and that's...
I thought it's a תני לוי, Tani Levi, the לוי Levi said
that...
No, לוי שאירע בו פסול Levi She’eira Bo Psul because... לוי Levi
isn't a תנא. Tanna.
Anyway.
What was פסול לינה Psul Lina then?
How does פסול לינה Psul Lina apply by a לוי?
Levi?
No, that would apply by a קרבן, Korban, the
פסול לינה. Psul Lina.
He's talking about a לוי. Levi.
Yeah, one second.
This is why I didn't prepare this part because I didn't think
I was starting here. One second.
I'm not sure. Mean
the...
No,
no, no, פסול טומאה ופסול לינה, Psul Tuma UPsul Lina, period.
Meaning I don't know what the לינה Lina is.
Right, so I thought because לוי Levi was saying like on...
talking about קרבנות. Korbanot. This isn't לוי Levi though. Okay. Because then
it doesn't make sense. Then how can it start with שאירע בו
פסול? She’eira Bo Psul?
But he's like talking about what was said before, ביציאתו. Beyetziato.
It could be I guess.
Fine, you're right. I'm sorry. Okay. Fine. It's strange that it's תני
לוי Tani Levi though.
It bothers me.
Anyway.
So
תא שמע... Tashma... fine, דתני לוי שאירע בו פסול ביציאתו. DeTani Levi
She’eira Bo Psul Beyetziato. The פסול Psul occurs as it leaves. So
מאי לאו פסול יציאה? Mai Lav Psul Yetzia? Doesn't that mean that
the פסול Psul itself is actually the leaving? לא. Lo. No, we
infer from this actually the פסול Psul happened while it was leaving
and the פסול Psul itself was not leaving. פסול טומאה ופסול לינה.
Psul Tuma UPsul Lina. Either being left over or becoming
טמא. Tamei. I'm sorry, you're right. So the קרבן Korban became פסול.
Pasul. So בעי רבי אלעזר פרים הנשרפים ושעירים הנשרפים משמשיצא רובו במיעוט
אבר מה. Ba’ei Rabbi Elazar Parim HaNisrafim VeSe’irim HaNisrafim Misheyatza Rubo Bemiyut
Ever Mah. So what happens if the
majority
of the animal leaves,
but the straw that breaks the camel's back for it to be
the majority of the animal is a minority of a single... limb.
Let's see if I can draw a cow well enough to do
this, right? So here's the, right, and then fine, okay, we're going
to do here's the cow. And it's, right,
it's half on either side, right? Here's the, that's a great cow,
right?
And then the
tail, looks like a turtle then.
It looks like, it doesn't matter. Okay. So the point is that
it became a רוב rov by מיעוט אבר, miut ever, that the
fact that a majority has left the בית המקדש Beit HaMikdash only
because of a minority of a single limb. Okay? Think that's what
we're talking about.
Okay. שיצא רובו במיעוט אבר מהו? Sheyatza rubo bemiut ever mahu? הא
מיעוטא דאבר בתר רובא שדינן ליה? Hach miuta de'ever batar ruba shadinan
leh? Do we consider the minority of the limb
after the majority of the limb that it's a part of and
therefore it's not considered to have left yet? והלו נפק ליה, Vehalo
nafak leh, it hasn't left yet, או דילמא בתר רובא דבהמה שדינן,
O dilma batar ruba debeheimah shadinan, or do we assess by the
majority of the whole animal? That is, it's a very interesting question.
Do we see an animal as a whole subdivided into its limbs
and when we're counting רוב rov of this, it's like, you know,
the presidential election or something like that, electoral college, popular vote versus
electoral vote. We take the majority of each of the states, and
right, it's something similar like this. Like, that is, you know, this
is Maine and this is Nebraska and this is Texas and whatever.
So the way the animal is quantified is in chunks of איברים,
evarim, or do we just assess the רוב rov of the whole
animal and we don't care about איברים? evarim? That's the question. So
פשיטא דלא שבקינן רובא דבהמה ואזלינן בתר רובא דאיברים? Pshita delo shavkinan
ruba debeheimah ve'azlinan batar ruba de'evarim? Shouldn't it be obvious that we
should just follow the majority limb by limb and not of the
whole animal? אלא שיצא... Ela sheyatza... so they say that that's פשיטא.
pshita. That is, we do consider the animal as subdivided into limbs
and we go by majority of each of the limbs. אלא שיצא
חציו ברוב אבר. Ela sheyatza chetzyo berov ever. No, no, no, it's
that it was half, exactly half and it was with the majority
of one limb. So slightly different, right? It's exactly down the middle
and the fact that it got to be exactly half, right, maybe
the tail a little bit different shape. That is, entire exactly half
of the animal is on either side, but it's because the majority
of... so it's sort of the borderline has scootched a tiny bit
up. So that is, there's more of the whole thing, but because
there's just enough, there we go, that's better, wait. Okay. So like
let's say the majority of the whole tail is outside but because
the minority of the rest of the body. So this is what
makes it exactly fifty-fifty. It's not fifty-one forty-nine, it's fifty-fifty, but it's
because of the majority of a single limb. Okay. So האי מיעוטא
דאבר בתר רוב אבר שדינן ליה? Hai miuta de'ever batar rov ever
shadinan leh? Do we say that the minority of this limb follows
the majority of the limb? והא נפיק ליה, Veha nafik leh, and
therefore it's considered to have left, או דילמא בתר בהמה שדינן ליה,
O dilma batar beheimah shadinan leh, or do we just go by
the animal itself and since it's fifty-fifty we still say it hasn't
left yet until there's a רוב, rov, and we say תיקו. teiku.
Okay.
Now we're up to...
it's probably all of these things.
Many of these are...
no, we had a whole bunch of questions we didn't even like
say תיקו teiku or not.
Right. So this actually has at least a justification. We'll see the
next, the next question is not addressed. So רבא בר רב הונא
מתני לה בגברי. Rabba bar Rav Huna matni lah begavrei. So Rabba
bar Rav Huna taught this הלכה halacha about considering the majority of
the animal, not about the majority of the animal by its actual
size, but he said that it applies to the rule of the
people working on the animal. Okay. דמתעסקין בו חמשה בני אדם. Demit'askin
bo chamishah benei adam. If there are five people involved in processing
this sacrifice,
ונפקו תלתא ופשו להו תרי. Venafku tlata upashu lehu trei. So three
people went out and two people are left.
So that's interesting. I mean, it could be that they had the
minority of the things, like one had the head, one had the
hoof, and then you know, and then one had something else small
and the two guys who are left had
like the חזה, chazeh, you know, the אליה.
alyah. So מאי? mai?
בתר רוב מתעסקין אזלינן? Batar rov mit'askin azlinan? Do we follow the
majority of those working on the קרבן korban and therefore three have
left, so it's, we say it's the majority? או בתר בהמה אזלינן?
O batar beheimah azlinan? Or since the animal is still in the
עזרה, azarah, it's not yet considered of יוצא? yotzei? That is, he's
willing to consider it יוצא yotzei even when the animal is still
in the עזרה. azarah. Why? I don't know, it doesn't make sense.
But because we assess, you counted it by the people working. He
said מתני לה בגברי. matni lah begavrei. That's... okay.
או בתר בהמה אזלינן? O batar beheimah azlinan? תיקו. Teiku. Okay. Another
question. בעי רבי אלעזר. Ba'ei Rabbi Elazar. Rabbi Elazar, the אמורא, Amora,
asked the following question. פרים ושיעירים הנשרפים שיצאו וחזרו. Parim use'irim hanisrafim
sheyatzu vechazaru. They left and then they came back.
מהו? Mahu? מי אמרינן כיון דנפקי להו אטמו להו? Mi amrinan keivan
denafki lehu itmu lehu? Do we say that since they left, they
got טמא? tamei? או דילמא כיון דהדור הדור? O dilma keivan dehador
hador? Or do we say the fact that they were able to
come back means that they're allowed to come back?
Because of the fact that they left means that they became טמא.
tamei. So because, you mean they became פסול? pasul? Is that what
you're trying to say?
No, because because that is אטמו להו, itmu lehu, that is that
they're מטמא בגדים. metamei begadim. That is, do we consider them,
do we consider them to be מטמא בגדים metamei begadim at that
point? That's the point.
Oh, that's what we mean? Okay.
Meaning,
meaning it becomes an אב הטומאה. av hatumah. Okay. So אמר רבי
אבא בר ממל תא שמע. amar Rabbi Abba bar Memel ta shema.
רבי אבא בר ממל Rabbi Abba bar Memel says: היו סובלין אותו
במוטות, hayu sovlin oto bemotot, היו סובלין אותו במוטות, hayu sovlin oto
bemotot, they were carrying it on a, on a frame, on a
wooden poles. הראשונים יצאו. harishonim yatzeu. So that is imagine we have
four, four guys שלעפינג schlepping out a cow on a מוט, mot,
or on a... so here's another cow. I'm great at sketching.
היינו במוטה בארבע? haynu bemota bearba?
Right. So here we have four guys carrying the cow.
Okay.
Okay. And then הראשונים. harishonim. So where's the border of the עזרה?
azarah? Let's put it here. Okay? So the first guys,
הראשונים שיצאו חוץ לחומת העזרה, harishonim sheyatzeu chutz lechomat ha'azarah, they exited
the עזרה. azarah. והאחרונים לא יצאו. veha'acharonim lo yatzeu. And these have
still remained in the עזרה. azarah. Okay?
So הראשונים שיצאו חוץ לחומת העזרה מטמאים בגדים. harishonim sheyatzeu chutz lechomat
ha'azarah metamin begadim. So they become so טמא tamei that they make
their clothes טמא. tamei. והאחרונים אין מטמאים בגדים עד שיצאו. veha'acharonim ein
metamin begadim ad sheyatzeu. And the ones who've stayed inside do not
become טמא tamei to the point that they make their clothing טמא
tamei until they actually leave. ואי סלקא דעתך כיון דנפקו להו אטמו?
ve'i salka datchach keivan denafku lehu itmu? So if you're going to
tell me, רבי אלעזר, Rabbi Eleazar, that as soon as they leave
they become מטמא בגדים, metamei begadim, that is that, sorry, that the
animal leaves that they become מטמא בגדים metamei begadim even if they
haven't left themselves, so הנך דאיכא גואי ליטמו. hanach de'ika gavai litmu.
You should say that those who remain inside will still become טמא.
tamei. Sorry, I drew the border in the wrong place.
The wall of the עזרה azarah is here. Okay. So these are
טמא tamei and these are still טהור tahor because they haven't left
yet. So he says this is a definitive proof from our משנה
mishnah that we should go by: Did the person leave yet? and
not by: Did the animal leave yet? Okay. ואי סלקא דעתך
הנך דגבאי ליטמו. ve'i
salka datchach hanach degavai
litmu. אמר רבינא. amar Ravina. רבינא Ravina can answer this. ותסברא? הכא
בעינא ואחר יבא אל המחנה וליכא.
vetisbra? hacha be'ina ve'achar yavo el
hamachaneh veleika. No, we say it's not because we go by the
people and not the animal. He says, no, it's because the פסוק
pasuk says explicitly ואחר יבא אל המחנה, ve'achar yavo el hamachaneh, that
after exiting, you become טמא tamei and then you're able to re-enter
the מחנה. machaneh. So if you haven't left the מחנה machaneh yet,
then that's why you're still טהור. tahor. It's not because we don't
go by the animal. It's that there's some other criteria. We go
by the animal, but with a hanging criterion, hanging conditional, which is
that you have to have left in order to be able to
re-enter.
So then what about the... so meaning he just agrees with רב
הונא Rav Huna then? Because רב הונא Rav Huna said... but the
גמרא Gemara said תיקו. teiku. He says בגברי מי עסקינן חמישה בני
אדם נפקו טפי פשיטא דהוה תרי. begavri mi askinan chamisha bnei adam
nafku tefi pshita dehavah tirei. So three went out and two were
left.
No, but that's not, that's different. That's for assessing the majority. Meaning
we still go by the
animal.
Oh, these two people haven't left yet or that's something else that
he was talking about רב הונא. Rav Huna.
But now we don't have a majority.
So certainly the, but who cares if a majority or not? It
has to do whether you left or not, not how many people.
Wait a second.
Sorry. Was that just talking about not פרים הנשרפים, parim hanisrafim, just
talking about just a general animal becoming טמא? tamei?
No, I think this is about פרים הנשרפים. parim hanisrafim. רש"י Rashi
says: לומר לך כיון שיצא פר חוץ למחנה אחת מטמא
בגדים אף על פי דלא נפקו גברי נטמו.
lomar lach keivan sheyatza par chutz lemachaneh achat metamei begadim af al
pi delo
nafku gavri nitmeu. Once the פר par leaves, מטמא בגדים. metamei begadim.
Even though the people have not left, they become טמא. tamei. אלא
לאו משום דאמר דאי הדר הדר וכל שכן אלו שמחוזרים ועומדים שהרי
לא יצאו? ela lav mishum de'amar de'i hadar hadar vechol sheken elu
shemechuzarim ve'omdim sheharei lo yatzeu? Or the question is, if they return,
and all the more so these that stayed there, because they didn't
leave. So that's the question. So this is a related question, but
this is a slightly different question.
Wait, so what was the question before?
The original question was when we're assessing whether the animal counts as
יוצא, yotzei, do we go by... do we go by
the people working on the animal or do we go by... it's
a similar, a similar question.
No, obviously you have to go by the people.
The people haven't left yet, so
they're not טמא.
tamei. So then why does the גמרא Gemara say תיקו?
teiku? I, I agree with you. It seems a bit strange because
it seems like a similar question. But let's continue. Okay. וליכא
אלא רבי אלעזר היכי בעי לה?
veleika ela
Rabbi Eleazar heichi ba'i lah? So since רבינא Ravina has this answer
to his question, or says the question isn't a very good question,
you have to reframe רבי אלעזר's Rabbi Eleazar question.
היכי בעי לה? heichi ba'i lah? כגון דנקיט ליה בכולבתא. kegon denakit
leh bechulveta. That is, they're not inside carrying it on a stretcher
type thing. All of the כהנים kohanim are outside and they're picking
up the cow on a long spear or something to lift it
out of the עזרה.
azarah. That sounds like a really bad way of doing it.
It does sound like a bad way of doing it, but it's
a way that you avoid some of the questions of being מטמא
בגדים metamei begadim because then you were never, meaning his question now
is since they were never inside, they're not, are they not considered
to have left or not?
So it means they'll never become טמא? tamei?
That the people will never become טמא tamei from this if they
do it this clever way. It sounds like. So תנו רבנן, Tanu
Rabbanan, a new ברייתא. braita. פרים ופרה ושעיר המשתלח, המשלח והשורפן והמוציאן
מטמא בגדים, והן עצמן אין מטמאים בגדים. Parim u’parah v’seir hamishtaleach, hamishaleach
v’hasorfan v’hamotzi-an metamei begadim, v’hein atzman ein metame-im begadim. Okay. That is,
the פרים parim and seemingly שעירים הנשרפים seirim hanisrafim as well,
the sacrifices which are burned outside, and the פרה אדומה parah adumah
which also is מטמא בגדים metamei begadim when you do the burning
outside, ושעיר המשתלח v’seir hamishtaleach and the scapegoat on יום כיפור Yom
Kippur which is pushed off of a cliff.
Then המשלח, hamishaleach, the person who takes the שעיר המשתלח seir hamishtaleach
to עזאזל, Azazel, and השורפן hasorfan or the people who burn the
sacrifices, והמוציאן v’hamotzi-an and the people who carry them out to be
burned, מטמא בגדים, metamei begadim, they become so impure that they impurify
their clothing, that is because they through this action, it's sort of
interesting
what defines the source of the טומאה tumah here, but let's at
least for now consider that by doing this action, the person becomes
an אב הטומאה, Av HaTumah, so that they're טמא tamei enough to
make their בגדים begadim טמאים. tme-im. והן עצמן אין מטמאים בגדים. V'hein
atzman ein metame-im begadim. But they themselves, that is the animals, now
it's a little bit strange, אינן מטמאים בגדים. einan metame-im begadim. That
if a piece of clothing touches the animal, that the clothing is
not טמא. tamei. That the source of impurity becomes the person involved
in the job but not the animal itself. Okay.
אבל מטמאים אוכלין ומשקין. Aval metame-im ochaleen u’mashkeem. But they can impurify
food and liquids. That is the general rule in טומאה tumah is
that an אב הטומאה Av HaTumah is right there. Where? Look in
purple.
Purple.
Right next to your cow. Oh there.
אב. Av. But he says but he says it looks like a
ראשון. rishon. Okay. Perfect. Great. Rabbi Linzer told us. So an אב
הטומאה Av HaTumah can be מטמא metamei all sorts of things. A
ראשון rishon can be מטמא metamei here. He wrote אוכל ochel here
for שני. sheni.
This also says אוכל. ochel.
Then you probably אדם. adam. No.
No, you can't have אדם וכלים. adam v'keilim. Up here you can
be מטמא אדם וכלים. metamei adam v'keilim. Right.
אב Av is מטמא אדם וכלים metamei adam v'keilim and a ראשון
rishon is אוכל, ochel, משקין. mashkeem. משקין. mashkeem.
Right. משקין ואוכלין mashkeem v'ochaleen always come together. And then to be
שלישי shlishi only תרומה וקדשים terumah v'kodashim and רביעי revii only קדשים.
kodashim. So, meaning, so
the the animals themselves are not considered to be an אב הטומאה.
Av HaTumah. So it's actually very interesting, right? The person carrying this
animal becomes an אב הטומאה Av HaTumah to make his clothing טמא,
tamei, but the animal itself is not a source of טומאה tumah
of אב הטומאה, Av HaTumah, it's considered like a ראשון לטומאה rishon
l'tumah to make food that touches it or whatever to be טמא.
tamei. Yeah.
But is the cause of the טומאה tumah because they're carcasses when
they're brought out of the בית המקדש?
Beit HaMikdash? No, because they're not נבלה. neveilah. That's נבלה neveilah is
מטמא, metamei, but that's because it's נבלה, neveilah, because it wasn't שחט-ed.
shacht These were שחט-ed. shacht So normally, you go to the butcher
shop, there's a kosher שחיטה, shechitah, it's not נבלה, neveilah, whatever, it's
not טמא. tamei. So there's a special rule for these sacrifices, explicit
in the תורה, Torah, that the person who's involved in processing them
becomes מטמא בגדים. metamei begadim. וכבס בגדיו וטהר אחר. V'chibes begadav v'taher
achar.
It's not because of the meat. It's not because of the carcass
of the animal. It's because you're doing this action.
And it happens when they leave the
sanctuary?
The cutoff point is when they leave, right. Otherwise you'd have people
with טמא tamei בגדים begadim walking around in the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, would be impossible.
No, but what I'm trying to understand is so like let's say
whatever it is, so they go out of the בית המקדש, Beit
HaMikdash, right? They're supposed to burn this thing. Yeah. Then they slip
and the פר par falls into a ditch and they can never
get it back out. So they're טמא tamei even though they didn't
burn it?
I forget. My sense would be, yeah, that the cutoff is when
they leave even if they didn't successfully, right? Don't we have something
about that?
I mean I always thought, you know, because they're doing it and
like it's going to get done and you
know, so it makes them טמא. tamei. Right, but what you're saying
taking them out and then what if they, I'm not sure about
that. I'd have to check.
And the other question I had was all of these animals except
the one to עזאזל, Azazel, they're going to be involved with the
slaughtering, they're going to be.
No, it's already been slaughtered. Well, the פרה אדומה, parah adumah, no.
עזאזל Azazel wasn't slaughtered at all. עזאזל Azazel one, right, the עזאזל
Azazel one
walks the whole way alive and is pushed off a cliff. The
פרה... parah... The פרה אדומה Parah Adumah walks alive to הר הזיתים
Har HaZeitim and then is slaughtered and burned. And the שעירים הנשרפים
Se'irim HaNisrafim and פרים הנשרפים Parim HaNisrafim are slaughtered in the temple
and the carcass is brought...
so it has nothing to do with this animal's state.
Right, that's the point, right. The Torah prescribed that the
טמא tamei never even touches a dead animal.
Right, he brings... pushes it and it dies down there.
Exactly. But it's just the process of being involved.
100%, 100%. And because actually all of them are called חטאת. Chatat.
So part of the idea of חטאת Chatat is on the one
hand removal and purification of sin and removal of טומאה, Tumah, at
the same time the חטאת Chatat animal itself in some way the
טומאה Tumah particles adhere to it in some way. So you can
sort of understand that the concern, the fact that these particular עבודות
Avodot involve the person involved becoming טמא Tamei is because you really
are transporting out a lot of טומאה. Tumah. פרים הנשרפים Parim HaNisrafim
and שעירים הנשרפים Se'irim HaNisrafim are for very severe sins or for
יום הכיפורים. Yom HaKippurim. They really get a lot more טומאה Tumah
particles on them. פרה אדומה Parah Adumah is called חטאת. Chatat. The
whole purpose of it is to purify from טומאת מת. Tumat Meit.
So it also has sort of a lot of טומאה Tumah energy
going on and certainly the אפר פרה Eifer Parah will be an
אב הטומאה Av HaTumah once it's processed as well. And then שעיר
המשתלח, Seir HaMishtaleach, of course, it's got all the sins on its
head and you have to... so if you sort of... if you
can force yourself to think in a sort of much more concrete,
kind of pre-modern way, they really are particles of טומאה Tumah adhering
to these animals more than other...
what we've seen to indicate if you didn't finish it, you know.
Right, so I'm not 100% sure.
But, you know, like let's say the שעיר המשתלח, Seir HaMishtaleach, it
runs away, like, you know, you haven't done your job. Right. Why
are his clothes... why don't his clothes receive טומאה? Tumah?
The clothes do. The person becomes so טמא Tamei that he is
מטמא בגדים. Metamei Begadim. He even makes his clothing טמא. Tamei.
No, he does, but why... it's the clothes touch the animal?
If clothes... if just an indescript clothes touches the animal?
Like your clothing touches that animal, they're not going to become טמא?
Tamei? Because you're not involved in this process.
Right, so because what is your status doing. Right. So the point
is that it's the process that conveys the טומאה, Tumah, not the
body of the animal. The body of the animal, but it does
to be מטמא משקין אוכלין ומשקין, metamei mashkin ochlin u'mashkin, that's a
lower level of טומאה. Tumah. Okay.
So בשלמא bishlama לרבי מאיר le'Rabbi Meir כדיתנא... kid'tana... so it's fine
according to the opinion of רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir כדיתנא דבי רבי
ישמעאל. kid'tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir holds like this
דרשה drasha from תנא דבי רבי ישמעאל, Tana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael, דתנא
דבי רבי ישמעאל detana d'bei Rabbi Yishmael על כל זרע זרוע.
al kol zera zerua.
Right. So this is the law of the טומאת אוכלין tumat ochlin
for food to become טמא, tamei, it has to have been הוכשר,
huchshar, it has to have become enabled or...
what's a better word for הוכשר? huchshar? Enabled to... I had a
better word that I don't remember. We'll go with enabled? That the
food needs to have liquid poured on it in order for it
to become susceptible to טומאה. Tumah. Okay. So food naturally by itself
without any... obviously if you go and water your plants and things
or whatever, but you go and wash an apple. So once you've
harvested the fruits, they're not able to become טמא tamei until you
wash it, until you dip it into dip or whatever. This is
why we wash our hands before we dip the כרפס karpas into
the liquid is because we don't want our hands to be טמא
tamei when we touch the food because we're putting it in liquid,
it kind of becomes susceptible to טומאה. Tumah. So על כל זרע
זרוע: al kol zera zerua: מה זרעים שאין סופן ליטמא טומאה חמורה
mah zeraim she'ein sofan litamei tumah chamurah just like food cannot become
טמא tamei as טומאה חמורה, tumah chamurah, that is, it cannot become
an אב הטומאה, av hatumah, וצריכין הכשר u'tzrichin hechshar and they need
הכשר, hechshar, they need to be wet with liquids in order to
become טמא, tamei, אף כל שאין סופו ליטמא טומאה חמורה צריכה הכשר.
af kol she'ein sofo litamei tumah chamurah tzrichah hechshar. So so too
anything which will never become an אב הטומאה av hatumah also needs
הכשר, hechshar, needs to get wet in order to make things טמא
tamei or to become
טמא. tamei. So יצאת נבלת עוף טהור שסופה ליטמא טומאה חמורה ואינה
צריכה הכשר. yatzat neveilat of tahor she'sofah litamei tumah chamurah ve'einah tzrichah
hechshar. But the exception to that is that the thing that that
comes to exclude is נבלת עוף טהור. neveilat of tahor. If you
eat a chicken that was not שחט shachted or you eat a
dove that was not שחט shachted or something like that, you go
and buy Perdue chicken, right, from the grocery store. So you take
that chicken and you eat it, it's not מטמא metamei like a
regular נבלה, neveilah, נבלה neveilah of a cow, which is מטמא metamei
when you pick it up or move it. But נבלה neveilah of
עוף of is מטמא metamei in the throat, מטמא בבית הבליעה. metamei
b'veit habliah. You have to eat one כזית kezayit of it and
swallow it and that's what makes you טמא. tamei. Okay. There's a
lot of למדות lamdus about that, it's a fascinating, strange, sort of
sui generis case in all of טומאה. tumah.
But the point is, that is a case which will be סופו
ליטמא טומאה חמורה. sofo litamei tumah chamurah. It will become an אב
הטומאה, av hatumah, that is when you eat that נבלה neveilah you
still become טמא tamei to be מטמא בגדים. metamei begadim. But, but
therefore it does not need הכשר. hechshar. It does not need to
get wet in order to make you טמא. tamei. אלא לרבנן, Ela
l'rabanan, what about the רבנן rabanan who reject this... the דרשה *drasha*,
אי אית להו דתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל *ee it lihu detane bei
Rabbi Yishmael*, so if they reject the דרשה *drasha* of רבי ישמעאל
*Rabbi Yishmael*, אפילו שעיר המשתלח se'ir hamishtaleach, *afilu seir hamishtaleach*. אי אית
ליה *ee it lei*,
so then they should say that even the שעיר המשתלח se'ir ha-mishtaleach.
*seir hamishtaleach* should also be מטמא metamei *metame* because what's the difference?
It's not dead, it's not alive, what? It shouldn't matter. אי לית
ליה אפילו פרה parah ופרים *ee let lei afilu para u-parim*. And
if they don't have the דרשה *drasha*, then they should, meaning they
should be consistent. Why is it that רבנן's Rabbanan *Rabbanan's* position, unlike
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir's *Rabbi Meir*, distinguishes between the שעיר המשתלח Seir
HaMishtaleach *seir hamishtaleach* and the other פרה אדומה *para aduma* and פרים
parim הנשרפים *parim hanisrafim*? Okay, so מנלן *minalan*? So what is the
basis for the position of רבנן Rabbanan *Rabbanan*? כי אתא רב דימי
*ki ata Rav Dimi*, when רב דימי *Rav Dimi* came from ארץ
ישראל *Eretz Yisrael* to בבל *Bavel*, he said, אמר אמרי במערבא *amar
amri bema'arava*, he said they taught this way in ארץ ישראל *Eretz
Yisrael*, צריכין הכשר טומאה tumah ממקום אחר *tzrichin hechsher tuma mimakom acher*.
They need to become, they need to have הכשר טומאה tuma? *hechsher
tuma*, that is they need to become wet from some other outside
source in order to be מטמא metamei *metame*, that is for these
פרים parim הנשרפים *parim hanisrafim* or whatever, in order
for
them to make something else טמא tamei? *tame*, they have to, they
have
to...
now I'm having a harder time keeping track. Do we mean to
be מטמא metamei? בגדים *metame bgadim* or we mean to be מטמא
אוכלין metamei ochlin ומשקין *metame ochlin umashkin*? I think, one second...
okay, yes, that, that as רש"י *Rashi* says, רש"י *Rashi* says that
even for these, so let's look at the רש"י *Rashi*. אמרי במערבא
צריכין הכשר טומאה tuma. ממקום אחר *amri bema'arava tzrichin hechsher tuma mimakom
acher*, הדתנא דבי רבי ישמעאל הכי קאמר *hadtane d'vei Rabbi Yishmael hachi
ka-amar*, כל שאין סופו sofo, לטמא טומאה חמורה tumah chamurah. *kol she'ein
sofo letame tuma chamura*, things which themselves do not become an אב
הטומאה av hatumah *av hatuma*, צריך הכשר טומאה tuma ממקום אחר *tzrich
hechsher tuma mimakom acher*, they have to become טמא tamei *tame* from
some other source, שיגע בשרץ או בנבלה *sheyigga basheretz o benevela*, ולא
שיתמהו מאליו *velo sheyitme'u me'elav*, that they, not that they just become
טמא tamei *tame* from their own status. אבל משסופו לטמא טומאה חמורה
tuma chamura, *aval mishesofo letame tuma chamura*, but things which will become
טמא tamei, *tame* on their own, that is because they become an
אב הטומאה av hatumah *av hatuma*, אין צריך ליגע בטומאה ומטמא טומאת
אוכלין ochlin מאליו *ein tzrich ligga bituma umitame tumat ochlin me'elav*, כגון
פרה ופרים *k'gon para u-parim*. So the difference is the פרה ופרים
*para u-parim*. The פרה ופרים *para u-parim* according to רבי מאיר Rabbi
Meir. *Rabbi Meir*,
because the פרה ופרים *para u-parim* as soon as they... their carcass
is itself מטמא metamei. *metame*. But the שעיר המשתלח Seir HaMishtaleach. *seir
hamishtaleach* its carcass is not מטמא metamei *metame*
only... no, sorry, ומטמא
טומאת אוכלין ochlin
מאליו כגון פרה ופרים
*umitame tumat ochlin me'elav k'gon para u-parim*, אבל חזי לטומאה מהא דעלמא
בעינן ולא בעלי חיים *aval chazi letuma meha d'alma ba'inan velo ba'alei
chayim*, that's the difference, sorry. The difference is that the שעיר המשתלח
Seir HaMishtaleach. *seir hamishtaleach* is alive and the פרה ופרים *para u-parim*
are dead. So פרה ופרים *para u-parim* are a dead slaughtered cow,
which is also called
beef.
So beef is food. So food is in the category of can
become טמא tamei *tame*.
Although you can't eat this.
You can't eat it, fine, that doesn't matter, it's food. It's beef.
But a שעיר המשתלח Seir HaMishtaleach *seir hamishtaleach* is a live goat.
A live goat is not in the world of טומאה tuma. *tuma*.
But the guy who המשלח *hamishaleach* it does become טמא tamei, *tame*
anyway.
Right. So the distinction for רבנן Rabbanan *Rabbanan* between those cases is
because, so it goes like this. That is according to רבי מאיר
Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir*, רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir *Rabbi Meir* said we
have this general rule and that's what it teaches. And רבנן Rabbanan.
*Rabbanan* say wait a second, if we have this, if we accept
this דרשה *drasha*, then even the שעיר המשתלח Seir HaMishtaleach. *seir hamishtaleach*
should need to become טמא tamei? *tame* from some other source in
order to be מטמא metamei, *metame* because it certainly isn't food, how
is it even going to become טמא tamei, *tame*? It doesn't make
any sense. And the opposite, if you don't have this דרשה *drasha*,
then how is it that the פרה ופרים *para u-parim* are מטמא
metamei, *metame* because they're, even though they're a dead cow and it's
meat but it's not yet become טמא tamei. *tame* from some other
source?
So מנלן *minalan*?
So כי אתא רב דימי *ki ata Rav Dimi*, אמר במערבא צריכין
הכשר טומאה tuma, ממקום אחר *amar bema'arava tzrichin hechsher tuma mimakom acher*.
That is if they became טמא tamei. *tame* from some other source,
the פרה ופרים *para u-parim*. Once they're food, they're, well not really
food, but they're beef. So beef can become טמא tamei *tame* and
therefore if they become טמא tamei *tame* from some other source, then
they could be מטמא metamei *metame* other foods and other liquids.
But why would the שעיר המשתלח *seir hamishtaleach* be מטמא metamei.
*metame* you then? It can't. That's the defense of רבנן Rabbanan *Rabbanan*.
But המשלח *hamishaleach* is טמא tamei *tame*.
Right, המשלח *hamishaleach* but not the שעיר *seir* itself. The שעיר *seir*
itself because it's a live animal cannot be מטמא metamei *metame* other
things.
Okay, like any live animal. Right, fine.
Right. So meaning if you don't accept רבי ישמעאל's *Rabbi Yishmael's* דרשה
*drasha*, then how do you explain why the פרה ופרים *para u-parim*
are able to be מטמא metamei *metame*? Oh, the answer is not
because they're a source of טומאה tuma *tuma* in themselves naturally, but
because they became טמא tamei *tame* by דין *din* of the fact
that they're food, that they're meat. So it was meat that became
טמא tamei, *tame* from some other source external to the whole discussion
and that's when they could be מטמא metamei בגדים *metame bgadim*. That
is when we said oh they're not מטמא metamei בגדים *metame bgadim*
themselves but they are מטמא metamei אוכלין ochlin ומשקין *metame ochlin umashkin*,
it's not actually telling me something about the status of the פרה
ופרים *para u-parim*, oh they're actually able to make food טמא tamei.
*tame* because they're a source of טומאה tuma *tuma*. No, no, no,
no, no, it just means they count as food. So if they're
food that became טמא, tamei then they could be מטמא metamei other
foods.
Okay, so let's say you touch this dead שעיר המשתלח, then are
you טמא? tame?
How are you going to touch it?
It fell at the bottom of the cliff. I don't know.
You touched its whatever, it's part of...
I'm trying to remember. I think we say no because I think
we say נעשה מצותו, na'aseh mitzvato, but I'm not 100% sure. I
think that's what we... No, but it's a נבלה. nevelah.
It's a נבלה. nevelah. It got pushed off a cliff. No, but
there's... oh, but there's... anyway, there's some back and forth about it.
I have to check. I have to check.
Okay. בעי רבי אלעזר, Ba'ei Rabbi Elazar, another question from Rabbi Elazar.
פרים ושעירים הנשרפים מהו שיטמאו אוכלין ומשקין בפנים כבחוץ? Parim use'irim hanisrafim
mahu sheyitamu ochlin umashkin bifnim kevachutz? So do we say that this
שעירים הנשרפים ופרים הנשרפים se'irim hanisrafim uparim hanisrafim should be מטמא אוכלין
ומשקין בפנים מבחוץ? metamei ochlin umashkin bifnim mibachutz? That is that they
should even while they're inside the בית המקדש, Beit Hamikdash, they could
be מטמא metamei other foods that touch them, or not? So מחוסר
יציאה כמחוסר מעשה דמי או לא? mechusar yetziah kimechusar ma'aseh dami o
lo? Do we say that because it hasn't yet been taken out,
it's like מחוסר מעשה, mechusar ma'aseh, it's missing a stage in its
processing and therefore should not be מטמא? metamei Or do we not
say that?
So בתר דבעי הדר פשטה, batar d'ba'ei hadar pashṭah, after he had
asked this question, he answered it himself. מחוסר יציאה כמחוסר מעשה דמי.
mechusar yetziah kimechusar ma'aseh dami. We treat the fact that it has
not yet been brought out like it is missing an action and
therefore it's not yet completed in its processing to the extent that
it should be מטמא. metamei. So therefore they will not be מטמא
metame. while they're still in the עזרה. Azarah. Okay. So בעי מיניה
רבי אבא בר שמואל מרבי חייא בר אבא, ba'a minei Rabbi Abba
bar Shmuel merabi Chiya bar Abba, Rabbi Abba bar Shmuel asked Rabbi
Chiya bar Abba: נבלת עוף טהור לרבי מאיר מהו שיטמא בכזית? nivlat
of tahor le-Rabbi Meir mahu she-itamei b'khazayit? Should we say that according
to Rabbi Meir's position that the carcass of a produce chicken or
whatever should be מטמא, metame that the שיעור shi'ur should be כזית?
kazayit? So דמחתה לארעא לא תיבעי לך דנקיט בפומיה לא תיבעי לך.
d'machtah l'ara lo tiba'i lach d'nakeit b'pumei lo tiba'i lach. So that
is how do we determine when you've become טמא tame regarding the
נבלת עוף טהור? nivlat of tahor? So
if it's דמחתה לארעא לא תיבעי לך, d'machtah l'ara lo tiba'i lach,
you can't ask that question because it's not... there's not even any
risk
because at that point it's still... you haven't even picked it up
yet.
You're only going to become טמא tame with this chicken if it's
when you eat it, when you swallow it. So while it's still
lying on the ground there's no question.
Sorry, sorry, let me go back a step. The normal size for
נבלה nevelah to be מטמא, metame. like a piece of... you go
to the supermarket and they have the porterhouse steak from the whatever
non-kosher beef company. So the שיעור shi'ur for נבלה nevelah to be
מטמא metame is what?
כזית. kazayit. It goes by the size, just a size of one
bite, a כזית. kazayit. The size for אוכלין ochlim to count as
an אב הטומאה av hatumah. or or not אב הטומאה av ha-tumah,
but to be to be מטמא. metame So when foods have become
טמא, tame in order to be מטמא metame something else, the size
minimum size is כביצה. kabeitzah. A bigger size, the size of an
egg.
The question is, I'm sorry, wait, did you just say it was
a כזית? kazayit?
No, נבלה nevelah the size is כזית. kazayit.
But נבלה nevelah is food.
No, נבלה nevelah isn't food, נבלה nevelah is נבלה. nevelah. No, meaning,
fine, but נבלה nevelah is a דין דאורייתא din d'oraita of... it's
an אב הטומאה. av hatuma It's מטמא metame because it's a נבלה.
nevelah. אוכלין ochlim became טמא tamei from some other source. They're a
ולד הטומאה vlad hatumah and now... so the rule of foods, like
my Cheerios... meaning a kosher שחוטה... shechted... a kosher piece of porterhouse
steak isn't a kosher steak I think, has a filet mignon.
I don't know, I don't eat meat.
You have to... Letterman know your cuts of meat.
So my... I got an apple, I washed the apple in the
sink, and then the apple touched the נבלה. nevelah. So now the
apple is a ראשון לטומאה. rishon l'tumah. Now the apple is טמא,
tamei okay? The שיעור shi'ur for the apple to be מטמא metame
something else is a כביצה, kabeitzah, a bigger size.
Oh, so let's say you have a really small apple, it's smaller
than an egg, it wouldn't be טמא? tamei But it's a בריה,
briah, I would think.
It could be... it's a מחלוקת machloket whether it could become טמא,
tamei, and I think everyone agrees that it cannot be מטמא metame
something else. I think that's right.
There's a מחלוקת machloket I think רש"י תוספות Rashi Tosafot and the
רמב"ם Rambam also about whether... whether the size of a כביצה kabeitzah
is to be מטמא metame or even מיטמא. mitamei. This is why
you need to pronounce Hebrew
carefully.
מטמא metame versus מיטמא. mitamei.
To impurify and to
become impure. Okay, so everyone agrees that this size is כביצה kabeitzah
for אוכלין and this is a bit of a
מחלוקת. machloket.
If you touch that meat in the, that נבלה neveilah meat, you
become טמא. tamei.
If you touch the נבלה, neveilah, you pick it up without even
touching it, you become טמא.
tamei But an עוף, of, if it was
an עוף, of, if it's chicken, only if you eat it, only
while you're swallowing. Right. So the question we have is, according to
רבי מאיר's Rabbi Meir position, do we
say מהו? mahu? שתטמא בכזית? She'tetamei bekazayis? Do we say that the
minimum size of non-kosher chicken, נבלת עוף טהור, nevelas of tahor, is
the minimum size כזית kazayis like נבלה? neveilah? Or is it a
bigger size? It has to be like אוכלין because the way you
become טמא tamei, is by eating it. So maybe it's more like
אוכלין and less like, by the way, because נבלת עוף טהור nevelas
of tahor is so sui generis, it's sort of its own thing,
much of מסכת טהרות Maseches Taharos is about that, then
it's
sort of we have all these questions about it because it's weird.
There's a whole interesting historical piece on that which we're not going
to talk about now, kind of thing that gets you kicked out
of ישיבה. yeshiva.
Okay.
So I guess he didn't bring it up.
Okay. The question is, so while it's still lying on the ground,
we don't even have a question. Because if you pick it up,
you're not going to become טמא tamei, anyway. There's no question about
that. It's עוף, of, so you're not going to become טמא tamei,
by picking it up. And if it's already in your mouth,
בפומיה לא תיבעי לך, be-fumei lo tiba'i lach, and while it's already
in your mouth, there's no question, because that already at that point
if there are other foods in your mouth then they'll become טמא
tamei, by touching it. And then those foods in your mouth will
מטמא metame you. Right? That is, I don't care—assuming
you're eating something else, obviously.
Right. So if you're chewing chicken, you're having chicken and—chicken sandwich. A
chicken sandwich. So the chicken, there's a piece of chicken, right? This
is נבלה. neveilah.
And it's in this is my mouth.
Okay. And I have bread also. So the chicken will become מטמא
metame the bread, and then the bread will make me טמא, tamei
so that would be even if it's כזית. kazayis.
Okay? Because that shouldn't matter. The question is what's the שיעור shiur
for swallowing the chicken, right? By itself.
Okay. דכי תיבעי לך דנקט ליה בידיה. De-chi tiba'i lach de-nakat leh
bidei. Sorry, that if you picked it up in your hand. Meaning
once I've picked it up in my hand and I'm about to
eat it, okay? So מחוסר קריבה כמחוסר מעשה דמי? mechusar kreiva k-mechusar
ma'aseh dami? Is basically the question sounds a little bit like do
we make a rabbinic extension of the rules of נבלת עוף טהור
nevelas of tahor to extend to apply even before you eat
it?
Sounds—the whole point is that you have to swallow it.
The whole point is that you have to swallow it. We say,
do we say, do we say that once you've picked it up
and you're about to eat it, that maybe that's
about to sin as if I sinned? No, it's not until I
sinned. Right?
Okay. I don't know.
So מחוסר קריבה כמחוסר מעשה דמי או לא? mechusar kreiva k-mechusar ma'aseh
dami o lo? Do we say that the fact that I haven't
yet put it in my mouth, it means it's missing an action?
It's missing the essential action of eating the נבלה, neveilah, or not?
So אבתרה דאביי הדר פשטה, Abasra de-Abaye hadar pashata, מחוסר קריבה לאו
כמחוסר מעשה דמי. mechusar kreiva lav k-mechusar ma'aseh dami. It's not comparable.
Why not? I mean, like, because obviously, because you didn't eat it
yet.
No, he says לאו כמחוסר מעשה דמי, lav k-mechusar ma'aseh dami, which
means that it is
טמא. tamei? No, if it's לאו כמחוסר, lav k-mechusar, then that means
it's as if I swallowed it, right?
We have all these טהרות Taharos topics and it's like, it's good,
but it hurts your brain a little bit. One sec.
No, okay, because it's according to רבי מאיר. Rabbi Meir Because
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir, says, כל שסופו לטמא טומאה חמורה אין צריך
הכשר,
kol she-sofo l-tamei tumah
chamura ein tzarich hechsher, right? Right.
So the fact is this, this כזית kazayis of נבלת עוף טהור,
nevelas of tahor, I'm going to eat it, so I'm going to
become טמא
as an אב הטומאה, av hatuma, right? So I'm—the chicken is סופו,
sofo right? It's exactly the same question, right? We have some object.
Oh, the board is a mess, right? So we're comparing two cases
now. I'm sorry, this is a little bit tricky and I didn't
get enough of a chance to prep, but that's part of the
issue. Okay. We have שעיר המשתלח. Okay.
Okay. This is a goat. It needs to go over here. When
it gets over here—meaning outside the מחנה. machaneh. Right. When it gets
over here, it will be מטמא. metamei Okay. So there is some
action
קריבה, kriva, maybe we could call it, that it needs to have
accomplished in order to be מטמא. metamei The נבילת עוף טהור neveilat
of tahor is also this, I need—it's only מטמא metamei בית
הבליעה beit hablia
when you swallow it.
When
it's in my throat, then I'll be מטמא. metamei So the question
is now, okay, so
רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir says, שעיר המשתלח is מטמא metamei. even before
you arrive, right because it's
סופו—it's sofo סופו מטמא metamei טומאה חמורה. tuma chamura, So then even
beforehand, some of the aspects of the טומאה tuma, have already started
to take effect.
Well, didn't everyone agree with that? That the moment you took it
out, you become טמא?
So the debate—the debate between רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir and רבנן is
specifically about the שעיר המשתלח. The פרים and the פרה everyone agrees
that
the moment you start walking out,
the moment you take it out. And that רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir
and the רבנן seem to disagree about the שעיר המשתלח. So now
we've drawn an analogy, right? The question from the אמוראים Amora'im from—from
רבי אבא בר שמואל Rabbi Abba bar Shmuel asks רבי חייא בר
אבא, Rabbi Chiya bar Abba, according to רבי מאיר, Rabbi Meir. who
says that the שעיר המשתלח is מטמא metamei, even from before you
reach the final stage, because it's sort of a continuous
process, could we make an analogy to נבילת עוף טהור neveilat of
tahor that even though really you're only מטמא metamei. when you swallow
it, but somehow you should already become טמא earlier on in the
process because—because the whole idea, you're picking it up in order to
eat it. Okay? That's the question.
We've drawn an analogy between them. Okay.
So just so I understand. רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is going to
say the same that what—what applies...
This is—this is עזאזל Azazel
and this is the mouth
and this is like in my hand
and this is like on the way.
Okay, and over here was—was while it's on the ground, on the
plate,
okay. This was in the עזרה. Azara.
So everyone agrees it's not מטמא metamei here, everyone agrees it is
מטמא metamei here, and the question is here. Everyone agrees it's not
מטמא metamei here, everyone agrees it is מטמא here, and the question
is what about here? I'm bringing it in my hand, I'm picking
up the chicken wing to eat it right now.
So רבי מאיר Rabbi Meir is going to say the moment you
step out of the עזרה Azara just like the פרים and the
שעירים? se'irim?
That's what he's saying.
But however, the רבנן would say no, it's not טמא until when?
Did we—did you ever figure that out?
That once you push it I guess or something like that, once—I'm
not a hundred percent sure.
Yeah, we didn't figure it out. Okay. But you can walk the
whole way, like ten miles, you didn't get to the mount.
I think so, you didn't—you didn't finish the מעשה. Ma'aseh. I think
so, I think so. I'm not sure.
Does it have anything to do with whether that bird is kosher
or not and
whether it has to be a kosher species of bird, it has
to be נבילת עוף טהור. neveilat of tahor. It has to be
a kosher species of bird which was not שחוט. shechted. It has
to be נבילה. Neveila.
But does the שחיטה shechting a bird make
it—okay, I guess it does. Not—not נבילה. Neveila. Right, right, right.
We're getting close to
the—no because I was thinking of the כהן Kohen does
מליקה.
Melika. מליקה Melika is a big issue because מליקה Melika
is
not שחיטה shechita or maybe it is. That's the big question about
מליקה. Melika. Is מליקה Melika something different than שחיטה shechita but it
at least removes the נבילה? Neveila? Right, we had this question before.
So that's the question, is מליקה Melika a kind of שחיטה? shechita?
Which was invented first, מליקה Melika or שחיטה shechita for birds?
Okay, we're not going to talk about this.
The chicken and the egg.
It's not chicken and the egg. Okay, איתמר, Itmar, a new—a new
challenge.
שלושה עשר דברים נאמרו בנבילת עוף טהור. Shlosha-Asar Devarim Nemru be-Neveilat Of
Tahor. There are thirteen הלכות halachot about the carcass of a dead
chicken, a dead kosher bird. וזה אחד מהם, Vezeh Echad Mehem, צריכה
מחשבה ואינה צריכה הכשר. tzericha machshava ve'eina tzericha hechsher.
Wait, what was the conclusion?
What you concluded—the conclusion was מחוסר קריבה לאו כמחוסר מעשה דמי mechusar
kreiva lav k'mechusar ma'aseh dami and therefore according to רבי מאיר it
should be מטמא even when it's in your hand. Sounds like.
It's hard to understand that, meaning like you know the whole point
I thought is that it's
only מטמא בית הבליעה, beit hablia, right? It seems very strange.
But it's רבי מאיר.
Yeah, but like, would he say that just with that?
Also this is an אמורא Amora saying what does a rejected שיטה
shita think about a different case? So רבי מאיר never actually said
that. It's an inference from רבי מאיר's position drawing an analogy to
a case that we—from a case that we don't פוסקים pasken like
to—to try to invent a case that we also won't פוסקים pasken
like. So there's no הלכתית halachic difference.
I'm supposed to take out the שעיר המשתלח. I'm not supposed to
eat נבילה. neveila. So you might want to say that like you
know in order—since I'm on a process I'm supposed to be doing
it might start earlier. But since I'm not supposed to be doing
this, I won't—it won't make him טמא until he actually does the
sin, right? You could say that.
Okay, we have more—we've only just got onto עמוד ב. amud bet.
We have ten minutes—no nine minutes.
Right, fine, but just let me round it out philosophically it's troubling.
I agree that it's a strange שיטה shita and I'm not a
hundred percent sold on it.
It's like making somebody responsible before they actually do it. That's exactly
what I'm saying.
No, but you're on the way, you're carrying the chicken leg to
your mouth, I mean that's the point, you've picked it up. Okay,
okay. So that's the question. By the way, the point as well,
but you still didn't swallow it. is that how much is נבלת
עוף טהורה neveilat of tehora like regular נבלה neveila that it should
be מטמא really sort of theoretically it should be מטמא when you
pick it up. We know sort of תכלס takhles it's only מטמא
in the mouth, but maybe there's some vestigial aspect? Well it's נבלה,
neveila, so maybe it's when you pick it up. So that, that's
also part of this. You're trying to bring it back to being
more like נבלה. neveila. Right?
Because if- because if נבלת עוף טמא, neveilat of tamei, then it
would be when I touched it, right?
Yes. When you touch it or you pick it up even if
you don't touch it, right? That's just like regular נבלה. neveila. Right.
Okay. שלושה עשר דברים נאמרו בנבלת עוף טהור וזה אחד מהם. Shelosha
asar devarim ne'emru bineveilat of tahor vezeh echad mehem. There are thirteen
things said about the הלכות halakhot said about the carcass of the
kosher bird, and this is one of them.
That is: צריכה מחשבה ואין צריכה הכשר. Tzericha machshava ve'ein tzericha hechsher.
It-
it needs מחשבה, machshava, that is you need to intend to eat
it. You have to have the plan to eat it. ואין צריכה
הכשר. Ve'ein tzericha hechsher. It doesn't need to get wet with liquid.
ומטמא טומאת אוכלין בכביצה. Umetamei tumat ochlin bekabeitza. And it makes other
things טמא just by touching it as a food, at the שיעור
shiur of an egg size. So מאי לאו רבי מאיר היא? mai
lav Rabbi Meir hi? Is this within Rabbi Meir's position? And therefore
it seems like a good proof. Why? Because it's מטמא אוכלין even
before- it's not when you're eating it. We thought the only way
עוף טהור of tahor makes you טמא is when you're eating it.
Sounds like it's מטמא even not while you're eating it. So we
say לא רבנן היא. lo Rabbanan hi. It must be the position
of רבנן. והא קתני רישא צריכה מחשבה. Veha katani reisha tzericha machshava.
The רישא reisha means you need מחשבה machshava ואין צריכה הכשר ve'ein
tzericha hechsher and it doesn't need to get wet.
What we just said. ומאן שמעת ליה האי סברא רבי מאיר? Uman
sham'at leh hai sevara Rabbi Meir? And the one who has that
position is Rabbi Meir. ומדרישא רבי מאיר סיפא נמי רבי מאיר. Umidereisha
Rabbi Meir seifa nami Rabbi Meir. So and since the רישא reisha
is Rabbi Meir, we should infer that the סיפא seifa should also
be Rabbi Meir. מידי איריא הא כדאיתא והא כדאיתא? Midi irya ha
kideita veha kideita? Is that really true?
וקתני סיפא שחיטה ומליקתה מטהרת טרפתה מטומאתה. Ukatani seifa shechita umelikatah metaheret
terefatah mitumatah. When you shecht it or if you do מליקה, melika,
then if it's a טרפה, tereifa, then it won't be מטמא. That
is, since you've shechted it or since you've done מליקה, melika, the
bird is not מטמא as a נבלה neveila because it wasn't נבלה.
neveila. And if it was a טרפה, tereifa, guess what, טרפה tereifa
isn't מטמא, only נבלה neveila is מטמא. So מאן שמעת ליה האי
סברא רבי מאיר? man sham'at leh hai sevara Rabbi Meir? Whose position
is that? Rabbi Meir.
So Rabbi Meir רישא reisha and סיפא seifa Rabbi Meir ומציעתא רבנן.
umitziata Rabbanan. So you're telling me now that the structure of this-
that this משנה mishna from טהרות, Taharot, the structure is that Rabbi
Meir is the beginning of it, the end of it is also
Rabbi Meir, and the middle part is the
רבנן's position? We say- אין רישא וסיפא רבי מאיר ומציעתא רבנן. In,
reisha veseifa Rabbi Meir umitziata Rabbanan. We have to end up saying
that there's this convoluted structure of the משנה mishna because we've sort
of insisted on reading these positions very rigidly. Okay. אמר ליה רב
המנונא לרבי זירא. Amar leh Rav Hamnuna leRabbi Zeira. Rav Hamnuna said
to Rabbi Zeira. לא תיתיב אכרעך עד דאמרת לי. Lo titive achre'ach
ad de'amart li. Don't- don't sit down until you've explained it to
me. הא מילתא נבלת עוף טהור לרבי מאיר מונין לה ראשון ושני
או אין מונין ראשון ושני. Ha milta neveilat of tahor leRabbi Meir
monin lah rishon vasheni o ein monin rishon vasheni. According to Rabbi
Meir, do we count ראשון ושני? rishon vasheni? Do we say that
the עוף טהור of tahor is מטמא other things a step down?
It's an אב הטומאה av hatuma and it's מטמא ראשון, metamei rishon,
and the ראשון rishon is מטמא שני? metamei sheni? So or do
we not? Do we say it has different rules because it's a
totally different kind of
טומאה? tuma, So אמר ליה כל היכא דמטמא אדם במגע. amar leh
kol heicha demetamei adam bemaga. Whatever makes a person טמא by touching
it. מונין בו ראשון ושני. monin bo rishon vasheni. Then that person
who became טמא, then will- will- you count further from there ראשון
ושני. rishon vasheni. כל היכא דאין מטמא אדם במגע. Kol heicha de'ein
metamei adam bemaga. Whatever does not impurify a person by touching it,
אין מונין בו ראשון ושני. ein monin bo rishon vasheni. So
it sounds like
that means to exclude this because it's not מטמא במגע, metamei bemaga,
it's מטמא בבית הבליעה. metamei bevet hablia. It's only מטמא if you
eat it.
Which is learned from the rule of שרץ, sheretz, that the שרץ
sheretz is sort of the classic example of a normal kind of
טומאה. And a שרץ sheretz if you touch it you become טמא.
כל אשר בתוכו יטמא. Kol asher betocho yitma. דהוה ליה הכלי ראשון
והאוכל שני. dehavah leh hakli rishon veha'ochel sheni. ונבלת עוף טהור, Veneveilat
of tahor, but the carcass of this kosher bird, לא מטמא אדם
במגע. lo metamei adam bemaga. It's not מטמא when you touch it,
and therefore we can't apply the normal rules of ראשון ושני rishon
vasheni to it because it's somehow totally sui generis. בעי מיניה רבי
זירא מרבי אמי בר חייא. Ba'ei mineih Rabbi Zeira meRabbi Ami bar
Chiyya. So Rabbi Zeira asked a question from Rabbi Ami bar Chiyya.
ואמרי לה מרבי אבין בר כהנא. Ve'amri lah meRabbi Avin bar Kahana.
Or maybe it was Rabbi- Rabbi Avin bar Kahana. הא דתנן חיבורי
אוכלין על ידי משקין חיבור לטומאה קלה ואין חיבור לטומאה חמורה. Ha
ditnan chiburei ochlin al yedei mashkin chibur letuma kala ve'ein chibur letuma
chamura. So okay, what are we talking about? You have a food,
you have another food, and now they're wet with a liquid, and
the liquid, the same wetness of liquid is touching both foods. Okay?
That's what we're talking about. So we say:
חיבורי אוכלין על ידי משקין. Chiburei ochlin al yedei mashkin. Foods that
are connected by a liquid. חיבור
לטומאה קלה. Chibur letuma kala. It counts as a חיבור chibur for
טומאה קלה, tuma kala, that is for if a ולד הטומאה, vlad
hatuma, some- person who's become secondarily טמא or for liquids to touch
or for foods to touch, that does count as a connection between...
between the two foods, ואין חיבור לטומאה חמורה, ve'ein chibur letuma chamura,
but it doesn't count as connected for the rules of טומאה חמורה,
the more strict, more severe טומאה of אב הטומאה, av hatuma it's
not connected enough because then you're trying to also make this into
a ראשון לטומאה, rishon letuma, which is also a higher level of
טומאה. So lower down the scale, because you're trying to create a
lower level טומאה, sometimes actually easier, because the threshold you have to
reach, the amount of טומאה you need to achieve is lower, so
it could be easier. Okay. That is if something touches this food,
then this one will also become טמא, but only if a let's
say ראשון rishon touches this food, then it'll be a שני, sheni,
and this also counts as שני sheni because they're מחובר. mechubar. But
if an אב הטומאה av hatuma. touches this food, then this one
will become ראשון rishon and this one is still טהור, tahor, or
the liquid will become טמא, but basically it will be much lower
down, it won't be considered connected. Okay?
So that's the question.
Wouldn't you think the אב הטומאה would cause a greater?
Well, that's exactly what's sort of counter-intuitive about this, which is that
in order for something of such a high level טומאה to transmit
also a relatively high level of טומאה, you need sort of more
strict criteria. But for also part of it is that the lower
levels of טומאה, some of them at least in certain cases are
rabbinic. They're only stringencies of דרבנן, derabbanan, so they could have additional
stringencies of, oh, we consider this connected anyway because we're worried about
our גזירות gezeirot and things like that, not because there's any real
intrinsic issue
there מדאורייתא. mid-Oraita. Okay.
Sorry, lost the spot.
חיבורי אוכלין על ידי משקין חיבור לטומאה קלה ואין חיבור לטומאה חמורה
מונין בו ראשון ושני או אין מונין בו ראשון ושני. chiburei ochlin
al yedei mashkin chibur letuma kala ve'ein chibur letuma chamura monin bo
rishon vesheni o ein monin bo rishon vesheni. So that is, do
we count in this kind of a situation where we've considered this
only counts as connected for טומאה קלה tuma kala but not for
טומאה חמורה, does it count, do we count one, two, three for
טומאות tumot or not? That's the question. אמר ליה כל היכא דמטמא
אדם מונין בו ראשון ושני. amar lei kol heicha demetamei adam monin
bo rishon vesheni. Whatever can make a person טמא, that is an
אב הטומאה. A שרץ sheretz touches this, נבלה neveila touches this, מצורע
metzora touches this, a זב zav touches it, whatever, then we would
say ראשון ושני. rishon vesheni. אין מטמאין אדם, ein metamein adam, but
if it's something with no power to make a person טמא, that
is something which became טמא only as a
ולד הטומאה, vlad hatuma, a שרץ sheretz touched a piece of food
or something, then that food touches this food, so אין מונין בו
ראשון ושני. ein monin bo rishon vesheni. In that case, we actually
wouldn't say ראשון ושני rishon vesheni anymore. The question becomes, well, if
that's a ראשון לטומאה rishon letuma that touched this, will we say
שני sheni for these at all? Are they not טמא? It seems
a little bit strange. I'm not sure exactly how this fits in
with other הלכות. halachot. But this is probably a good place to
stop, and I'll pick up here where Rabbi Linzer is going to
be away for שבת, shabbat, so I'm going to be doing the
דף daf tomorrow. Okay. Bye-bye. Have a great day.